<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.2//EN" "http://apache.org/forrest/dtd/document-v12.dtd">
<document>
	<header>
		<title>Servomaster</title>
	</header>
	<body>

		<section>
			<title>What is Servomaster?</title>

			<p>

				Servomaster is a platform and hardware Independent RC servo
				controller driver.

            </p>

		</section>

		<section>

			<title>Mission Statement</title>

			<p>

				Servos are commonly used in radio controlled modeling and robotics
				applications. More and more vendors are manufacturing
				hardware servo controllers that can be controlled by a personal computer
				or embedded hardware. Initial list consisted of now defunct <link href="site:ferret">FerretTronics</link> FT639 &amp; FT 649,
				<link href="ext:phidgets/">PhidgetServo</link>,
				<link href="ext:seetron">Scott Edwards Electronics, Inc. (Seetron)</link>
				<link href="ext:ssc2">SSC</link>, some
				<link href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PIC16x84">PIC16x84</link> based; later came
				<link href="ext:pololu">Pololu</link> and
				<link href="ext:parallax">Parallax</link>; much more are out there now. 

            </p>

			<p>

				However, almost all of them (with
				<link href="site:credits">notable exceptions</link>
				), being in the hardware manufacturing business, care little about
				providing a consistent interface for the servos and controllers. This
				is understandable, but disappointing, because all the servos
				are just about the same, and the basic functionality of the
				controllers is just about the same.

			</p>

			<p>

				This <em>can</em> and <em>is</em> being fixed, right here.

			</p>

		</section>
		
		<section>
		
			<title>What Exactly Is Offered</title>
			
				<ul>
					<li>Uniform set of platform and hardware independent abstractions representing servos and servo controllers;</li>
					<li>Motion <link href="site:transform">transitions and transformations</link>;</li>
					<li>Way to introspect and perform capabilities discovery on your hardware;</li>
					<li>Generic serial and USB implementation, suitable for extension for virtually any hardware;</li>
					<li>Growing set of <link href="site:relnotes">concrete hardware drivers</link>.</li>
				</ul>
			
		</section>
		
		<section>
		
			<title>How To Stay In Touch</title>
			
			<p>
			
				<link href="ext:dz_blog">DIY Zoning</link> blog has
				a dedicated <link href="ext:dz_blog_servomaster">Servomaster</link> section.
				Subscribing to its RSS Feed is the best way to stay aware of updates.
				
			</p>
			<p>
			
				New releases can be found at <link href="site:downloads">SourceForge Downloads Page</link>.
			</p>
			
		</section>

		<section>

			<title>Brief History</title>

			<p>

				ServoMaster was created as a complimentary project necessary to
				satisfy the needs of another project, <link href="ext:dz">DIY Zoning</link>.
				Being lazy (hate to rewrite the same code ten times), I decided to
				just make it generic from the very beginning. It turned out to be
				fun. Then, <link href="ext:phidgets">Chester</link> showed up, and it
				started to be really fun ;)

			</p>
		</section>

	</body>
</document>
