<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.2//EN" "http://apache.org/forrest/dtd/document-v12.dtd">
<document> 
  <header> 
    <title>ServoMaster: Donations</title> 
  </header> 
  <body> 
    <section>
        <title>Your help is appreciated</title>
        
        <p>
        
            ServoMaster Project is now accepting donations.  The donations
            are accepted through a mechanism that was set up by <link
            href="http://sourceforge.net/">SourceForge</link>.  If you feel
            like making a donation, you can do so by visiting a <link
            href="http://sourceforge.net/donate/index.php?group_id=34418">ServoMaster
            Project Donations</link> page.  Currently, 5% of every donation
            is granted to SourceForge - they did an excellent job of
            supporting this project (and countless others).
            
        </p>
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Why make a donation?</title>
        
        <p>
        
            Well, first of all, because it can help to make this project
            better. Even as it is, it makes a significant contribution to
            <link href="ext:dz">DIY Zoning</link>, allowing it to take a
            second place on Google search on "temperature zoning", right
            after Honeywell.
        
        </p>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>There are things other than money</title>
        
        <section>
            <title>Feedback</title>
            <p>
            
                It is very difficult to find an answer if you don't know the
                question. Internet is endless, and it's easy to drown, and
                sometimes impossible to find something, even if you know
                where to look for it.
                
            </p>
            <p>
            
                <link href="https://sourceforge.net/mail/?group_id=52647">Let us know</link> about your pains.
                
            </p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Hardware</title>
            <p>
            
                Hardware is cheap.
                 
                <br/>
                 
                Software is expensive.
                 
                <br/>
                 
                Software development is <strong>outrageously</strong>
                expensive.
                 
                <br/>
                 
                We <strong>know</strong> how to do it, and we've
                <strong>done</strong> it, repeatedly.
                 
            </p>
             
            <p>
            
                Donate hardware, and get the working drivers available to
                all your customers in a few days. And the name of your
                company gets into the <link href="site:credits">Hall Of
                Fame</link>. And your customers will know you care about
                them.
                 
            </p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Wishes</title>
            <p>
            
                 <link href="https://sourceforge.net/mail/?group_id=52647">Tell us</link> what you always
                 wanted to have but never could - your wish may come true. 
                 Some people have requirements that others can't even think
                 about but find them useful when they become available. For
                 example, believe it or not, but there was a person whose
                 significant other was driving him mad because she couldn't
                 learn how to deal with the thermostat...
                     
            </p>
            <p>
                     
                If you have a wish and want to fulfill it, you may have
                just come to a right place.
                
            </p>
        </section>
        
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
