<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.2//EN" "http://apache.org/forrest/dtd/document-v12.dtd">
<document>
    <header>
        <title>ServoMaster: Observations on Mini SSC II Servo Controller</title>
    </header>
    <body>
    
        <section>
            <title>Foreword</title>
            
            <p>
            
                I don't have this controller, and all the code was written
                based on the protocol specification published at Scott
                Edwards Electronics, Inc. site and in the <link
                href="site:pololu">Pololu</link> servo controller user
                manual.  It is possible that I've made a mistake somewhere -
                if so, I'd appreciate if you could fix the code and send me
                the patch - I mean, I don't think there'd be many mistakes
                in 135 lines of documented code. If you want to <link
                href="site:donations">donate the hardware</link> - well, the
                better.
            
            </p>
            
        </section>
        
        <section>
            <title>Summary</title>
            
            <p>
            
                Mini SSC II is one of the oldest controllers available on
                the market. It doesn't support any of more advanced features
                available from later controllers, but I guess it's still
                pretty popular due to the fact that it's been out there
                forever.
            
            </p>
            
        </section>
        <section>
        
            <title>Good Things</title>
        
            <ul>
            
                <li>
                
                    Simple protocol - a driver takes 10 minutes to write;
                    
                </li>
                <li>
                
                    Modest protocol overhead of 33% (more, than <link
                    href="site:ft639">FT639</link>, less than <link
                    href="site:pololu">Pololu</link>) - this matters since
                    it only supports 2400 or 9600 baud;
                    
                </li>
                <li>
                
                    Stackable. You can connect multiple controllers to the
                    same serial line, provided you've configured the servo
                    numbers beforehand, all the way to 254 (however, you'd
                    have to order a special firmware version if you want to
                    have more than 15 servos).
                    
                </li>
            
            </ul>
            
        </section>
        <section>
        
            <title>Bad Things</title>
        
            <p>
            
                Two power sources required - this was a turnoff for me back
                in 2001, when I was considering my first servo controller.
            
            </p>
            
        </section>
        <section>
        
            <title>Note on Stacked Configurations</title>
        
            <p>
            
                According to documentation, Mini SSC II controllers can be
                stacked (multiple controllers connected to the same serial
                port).
                
            </p>
            <p>
            
                Servomaster currently doesn't support sparse servo arrays,
                so this feature is not explicitly supported.  This is due to
                the fact that none of servo controllers supported report
                back what servos are connected and what aren't.
                
            </p>
            <p>
            
                However, it is possible to support all the servos on all the
                controllers connected - all you have to do is change the
                value returned by <code>getServoCount()</code> in the
                implementation class.
                
            </p>
            <p>
            
                If you need this feature, <link href="site:lists">let us
                know</link> - it's trivial to implement.
                
            </p>
            
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title>Conclusion</title>
            
            <p>
            
                Since I've never dealt with this hardware myself, there will
                be no conclusion. However, I'm open to publishing other's
                feedback, should someone volunteer to contribute it.
                
            </p>
            
        </section>

    </body>

</document>
