<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.2//EN" "http://apache.org/forrest/dtd/document-v12.dtd">
<document>
    <header>
        <title>ServoMaster: Observations on USB PhidgetServo v3.0</title>
    </header>
    <body>
        
        <section>
            <title>Summary</title>
            
            <p>
            
                This USB controller is the most stable and reliable servo
                controller I was able to get a hold of so far.
                
            </p>
            <table>
                <caption>Supported Features</caption>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <link href="site:contract_removable">Removable Device</link>
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>

                        Individual Servo <link
                        href="site:meta_servo_range_min">min</link>/<link
                        href="site:meta_servo_range_max">max</link> preset

                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <link href="site:meta_controller_silent">Silent Operation</link>
                    </td>
                </tr>
            </table>
            
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Release Notes</title>
            
            <p>
            
                Keep in mind that the hardware version for which this driver
                is provided is different (later) from the one described on
                the <link href="ext:phidget_quad">site</link>.  Since the
                Phidgets are evolving rather rapidly, the versioning,
                capabilities discovery, and support are expected to be a
                standard part of this driver. This document describes the
                hardware and the driver for USB PhidgetServo v3.0, for
                information on upcoming v4.0 look <link
                href="site:phidget_servo8">here</link>.
                
            </p>
                
        </section>
        
        <section>
        
            <title>Good Things</title>
        
            <ul>
            
                <li>
                
                    Reliable as hell.  The manufacturer wants me to make it
                    fail, I couldn't;
                    
                </li>
                <li>
                
                    Simple to use.  Plug in the USB, plug in the servos, go;
                    
                </li>
                <li>
                
                    Versatile. One of the servos is powered by the USB bus,
                    so it is possible to start playing with it right away
                    even without external power supply;
                    
                </li>
                <li>
                
                    Precise. The actual controller is controlled by the
                    pulse timings it has to provide to the servos. Usable
                    range for the servos is somewhere from 200us to 2100us,
                    which makes the resolution of 1900 steps. If your servo
                    is capable of working in a wider pulse range, you get
                    more steps available;
                    
                </li>
                <li>
                
                    It is a USB HID device, enough said;
                    
                </li>
                <li>
                
                    The bandwidth is limited by the servo inertia, not by
                    the protocol or interface;
                    
                </li>
                <li>
                
                    Flexible. You can control properties on per-servo basis;
                    
                </li>
                <li>
                
                    Customizable. To the best of my understanding, the
                    manufacturer will provide custom solutions - different
                    number of servo outputs per board, different protocol
                    support and basically whatever you need.
                    
                </li>
            
            </ul>
            
        </section>
        <section>
        
            <title>Bad Things</title>
            
            <p>
            
                 As of now, it's still a write-only device. I don't think
                 it's such a big deal for this device - otherwise, it's near
                 perfect. The only extra ability that I would like to see is
                 the hardware level transition support, but admittedly,
                 that's a lot to ask ;)

            </p>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title>Conclusion</title>
            
            <p>
            
                Beauty incarnated :)
                
            </p>
            
        </section>

    </body>

</document>
